so
do
[Music]
hello everybody good day good morning
good evening to all of you wherever you
are i hope you're doing very well and
welcome to the 91st live episode of ask
abhijit
as you know we are discussing the
situation in ukraine today before i
begin a very brief announcement i have
created a separate short clips channel
here is the
link
to the channel it's youtube.com object
java.clips the link is also in the
description below so henceforth going
forward all the short clips will be
uploaded to that separate channel so in
case you want to stay
you know
in case you want to stay up to date
please subscribe to the short clips
channel right
okay so uh
as you know today we are i'm taking
questions from the comments that you
have
that that you have asked so let's let's
get right into it let's begin with
question number one
okay this is by samarth what is the
exact objective of the russian invasion
is it to conquer the entire ukraine or
just remove the pro-west government or
occupy eastern ukraine
will china be economically controlling
russia now after all the sanctions
it seems like russia might fall into a
debt trap
and so on is china the biggest threat
now right a good question so the last
live streams that i did was were one
week ago 26 27 february the russian
intervention in ukraine began on the
24th of february so the the last live
stream at that time the things were the
situation was very much fluid
we have far more clarity today
so what do we know about the russian
objectives we know that the russian
army the russian armed forces are
proceeding very systematically there is
no hurry they are not trying to rush
into anything they are proceeding very
slowly systematically not very slowly
but very systematically so what seems to
be the objective the objective has never
been
explicitly announced but what it looks
like is
it looks like mr putin wants to capture
whatever territory he intends to capture
as intact as possible as you as we know
the internet is still working in ukraine
right uh all communication lines are
open uh electricity is available in most
of the places there are uh
i mean the the invasion uh
forces are even obeying the traffic laws
traffic rules and everything so it's a
very uh
systematic invasion they're not trying
to engage in any big battles
they are not
they're trying as far as possible to
avoid civilian casualties there are lots
of video circulating where people are
coming face to face with russian
soldiers carrying ukrainian flags and
protesting and the russians are just
looking at them they're not doing
anything there's no violence brutality
and all that
so
we can say that there is very uh there
is a very clear
plan that they are following so the
objective of the invasion seems to be
regime change
what seems to be the objective is they
want to remove the
nato puppet government that was
installed
beginning in 2014 at that time it was a
different president today we have uh
the the actor comedian president
uh zalinski right so
he is obviously a pro nato pro west
person so he most likely
the intention is to remove him and to
replace him with somebody else who is
pro-russia so replace a pro-nato puppet
with a pro-russia puppet well that's how
things work and the donbass
region will be most likely
be annexed into russia that's one
possibility
and the eastern part of ukraine would
become more or less
part of russia possibly uh see the thing
is
if you look at ukraine there are lots of
russian-speaking people there the only
place where i believe there is a
ukrainian-speaking majority is the
western one-third of the country so
maybe that may be left aside
possibly so we still don't
know exactly what the objectives are
what i can definitely tell you is that
there is going to be regime change
in kiev
so the current government will be
removed in a different new new
government pro-russia government will be
installed and
that's that seems to be the objective
so i don't know if the entirety of
ukraine will be conquered that's not
what's happening right now they have
very clear military objectives and
they're moving with pinpoint precision
so definitely
a regime change is going to happen
that's what i can tell you for sure
that's the amount of clarity we have as
of today
okay the next bunch of questions is
about
why is russia dragging the process of
war is there any uh motive hidden behind
this tactic anif says the war is being
dragged down for dragged on for longer
than expected by mr putin he must have
anticipated kf to fall within two three
days of the attack
if it is true how do you think it will
impact the conflict will mr putin be
more aggressive to get care as soon as
possible and rishikesh says if russian
defense forces are so powerful why is it
taking so much time for them to achieve
their objectives okay so this is the
impression that the media is giving us
they are saying that the russian
invasion or the intervention has been
bogged down uh why why is it that they
have not not been able to take cave and
so on and the comparison that we have is
the various american invasions of
various parts of the world
let's say the 2003 invasion of iraq or
the invasion of afghanistan or the
invasion of libya and so on so forth
yugoslavia because of so many things
and typically when the americans
invade a country they go shock and awe
so they begin with a with a
massive aerial bombardment all the
videos are still available on youtube
i'm sure baghdad etc they just flatten
the place
and then they move in because there is
nothing left to resist them so and when
they are moving in if there is any
resistance of the if there is anything
in the way they just annihilate that
right friend four doesn't matter just
wipe everything out then move in and
then you establish peace and democracy
in whatever wasteland is left so that is
the american way of doing things the
russians are not doing that
the russians are not trying to flatten
ukraine they're not trying to destroy
the cities right they're not where's the
russian air force they're doing nothing
with the air force the air force is just
there some helicopters here and there
one or two aircraft once in a while but
you don't see any major involvement of
the air force and yet we know that in
the first two three hours the russians
had achieved complete air supremacy over
ukraine whatever the media is telling
you doesn't matter because if you see
there are so many long 40 mile long
columns of russian vehicles going
towards kiev if the ukrainian air force
was still active how come there is
nothing
they are not able to target the convoys
of the russians it proves that the
ukrainian air force has been neutralized
completely the russians have complete
air supremacy and they are choosing it
not to use their air force
because they don't want to well they
don't want to do bombardment the way the
americans do so
that's what we know
now if you want to look at the uh let me
let me show you some
images
one second so we will know
how how it's working
so
this
yeah this is a map of the invasion on
the second day
okay the second day after the invasion
this is how it was so the yellow
territories are the one the red one is
donetsk in luhansk which the russians
already controlled to some extent the
yellow territories are the ones that the
russians wanted to advance into and
there were there was some military
action going on in these areas so this
is on day two
this is day four the red territories are
the ones the russians had already taken
control of
right
so you can see over here there is this
encircling happening the blue areas are
where the ukrainian armed forces are
present and they are trying to encircle
them the russians right so this is day
four
this is uh i think a day or so before
today so you can see there is
significant progress happening
so in just 10 days they have achieved
this much progress this is faster than
the american invasion of
of sort of of iraq
and it is faster than the german
blitzkrieg
into france in the second world war
so it may look like a slow
steady thing it's not slow at all it is
moving at very good pace
the way the media portrays it will be
like like nothing is happening uh the
media commentators especially the
western media they're saying that the
invasion is going to fail and mr putin
is going to be ousted because this is a
disaster and so on so forth but look at
the progress you're seeing on the maps
there are two ways of looking at things
you see
one thing is to look at social media
look at all the propaganda that's that's
cropping up
videos from
they will show some destroyed russian
vehicles here or
or some helicopter that's been shot down
there so you get all these
different data points there is one way
of looking at it that is the bottom up
approach of examining a military
campaign there is a different approach
called the top down approach in which
you look at maps you look at the big
picture
and i just showed you the big picture
that is the correct way of looking at
the progress
of a military campaign and you can see
the steady
steady increase in the territory that
the russians are controlling and also
you can see a very clear purpose in what
they're trying to achieve they're trying
to encircle the ukrainian armed forces
and then they will hopefully make them
surrender i hope so and they want to
take care but they're not they're not
going into care they are also
surrounding cave and then they will wait
so
it's a very systematic way of doing
things so there is no dragging that's
happening it's doing it's it's happening
very systematically step by step and
they are trying their best not to cause
any civilian casualties or or any
avoidable
damage as far as possible to civilian
infrastructure and all that that's what
they are trying to do this is a war in
war once you
set things in motion you can't control
everything but they are trying their
best not to
cause any unnecessary destruction
okay ashish says my question is that has
putin underestimated the defense power
of ukraine or is there a bigger plan
like we have only seen phase one the
bigger strike is just is the bigger
strike is yet to come
so mr putin has not underestimated the
defense power of ukraine where is the
defense
uh
the ukrainian armed forces are not
i mean what are they doing is have you
seen a single proper battle between two
armies two armed forces have you seen
any artillery battle any air force
battle
have you seen any of that or any missile
battle which in which you see
equal amounts of firepower from both
sides you don't see any of that where
are where are the ukrainian armed forces
right they have been subdued they are
essentially hiding and they may
hopefully surrender i mean the russians
are
have way outmatched the ukrainians and
as you can see the ukrainian air force
is not to be seen anywhere i think
within the first three hours or so the
new the russians had neutralized the
ukrainian air force
with these very
targeted pinpoint uh cruise missile
strikes at various airports and various
radars
and uh
things such as that military
installations so i think that mr putin
has not underestimated anything you
don't
plan for a long time and then end up
underestimating something so this is
so what what we are seeing is tactics
and strategies that hearken back to the
ussr days the soviet army used to use
similar tactics for instance if you look
at the uh
if you look at the picture
if you look at this map here
then you will see in this region if you
can see my mouse pointer
you can see there is this blue region
here where is the where the ukrainian
armed forces are
entrenched and they are being encircled
by the russian army so this strategy is
called the cauldron strategy they are
encircling the opponent creating a
cauldron a closed cauldron and then they
can do as they wish with them this is a
very ancient strategy it it the soviets
used it the ussr used it but even the
mongols used it ching is khan the great
conqueror used the same sort of similar
tactics and strategies even while
hunting the mongols would do that you
know they would encircle a piece of
woods or forest and then they would trap
a number of animals in there and then
they would hunt them
as they wished so this is a very old
strategy and that's what the
russian armed forces are using today
and so so
what we see is that there is no question
of any underestimation or the media will
portray things in a way in in a variety
of ways
if we look at social media then one
could
conclude or one could
say that ukraine is winning the war on
social media
but on the ground there's a whole
different reality which we are seeing
through the maps
so that's just what it is it's that's
just how it how the campaign is
progressing
satna says
this video did not age well a lot of
civilians have lost their lives and
nathan said
you said there will be no harm to
civilians but people are dying including
indians what's your take on this okay so
last week i had said when on on day two
or day three of the of the intervention
i had said that the russians will try
their best not to target civilians they
will try not to harm any civilians
that's what i said
and now people have interpreted that
as me having said that not a single
civilian will die
that's not what i said in a military
conflict even if you try your best not
to cause any civilian casualties when
the opposition is arming civilians when
they are placing hostages as human
shields in military installations you're
gonna have loss of life
i never said not a single civilian will
die that's impossible in a conflict i
said the russians will try their best to
minimize civilian casualties they will
not go and target civilians they will
only target military installations and
that is precisely what we have seen over
the past 10 days they are doing pinpoint
strikes they are targeting only military
installations they are not targeting
civilians lots of videos are there when
civilians are confronting the
russian soldiers who are carrying
weapons and the russians are being very
patient and very restrained
right so they are not targeting
civilians yes civilians will die if the
ukrainians place civilians as human
shields inside military installations we
know that's happening
and if a civilian goes for a walk when
there's a artillery barrage happening
that civilian will die if they're that
stupid right so casualties happen in war
if you compare the number of casualties
that you fo that you saw in the american
invasion of iraq
first 10 days and this particular
russian military campaign the difference
in civilian casualties will be
shockingly different
there are very few
civilian casualties in this campaign
compared to what the americans did in
iraq or in afghanistan or in
libya or anywhere else in the last 20 30
50 100 years
so that's what i meant and that is
precisely what's happening and i never
said there will be no harm to civilians
i said the russians will try to minimize
civilian casualties they will do their
best not to
hurt any civilian but this is war man
some people unfortunately will die that
is the sad thing about about wars
some people start the war and the people
who end up suffering the most are the
innocent civilians that's what happens
always in wars so the russians are
trying their best not to do that because
they do not see the ukrainians as a
separate people as a foreign nation the
ukrainians are the same as the russian
people they are slavic people and so on
i've gone into the history in the past
so that's the reason why the russians
are trying their best to minimize
civilian casualties
and
damage to civilian infrastructure
okay nobody gonna talk about naveen who
got direct shot from the russian army
according to whatever dungar singh jawan
said you said the russians will never
kill any country citizens but our
student is dead in the shelling of the
russian army and ajay says an indian is
already killed you were saying in your
videos that russian military have no
intention of harming civilians
okay so this is a lot of the same themes
as what i what the previous question i
took i never
said
so there are two questions being asked
over here there's a specific question
and a more general question okay about
naveen so we had this indian student
very unfortunate very tragic naveen
shekhar i think his name was
the death was announced on first of
march i believe
so he died in the city of kharkiv
and initially it was believed that he
was he died in shelling
but later it emerged through video
evidence that he was shot somebody shot
him all right
now
when naveen was shot
in kharkiv the russians were not in
kharkiv
the russians were outside kharkiv far
away
many many kilometers away there was not
a single russian
soldier in kharkiv and yet naveen
was shot
to death
now we know that in kharkiv the
ukrainians had been arming civilians the
ukrainian government had issued ak-47
and other weapons to civilians they had
also freed
criminals
and given them weapons now what can you
can you put two and two together to
understand what happened to our guy
naveen
the poor guy
was in a in a bunker in a bomb shelter
all night then once the curfew was
lifted for a few hours he went out to
get some provision some food and water i
i suppose
and then we find that he has been shot
and there was not a single russian in
the city
who is to be held responsible for this
the russians
come on
he was shot
clearly
not by a russian so who else can it be
somebody on the ukrainian side either a
civilian who had been given weapons or a
criminal was released by the by the
ukrainian government that's all i can
say
right now i did say the russians will
never
willingly or knowingly hurt an indian
citizen they will do their best to
evacuate the indian citizens that's what
i said
but this is war i also said the russians
will try their best not to hurt
civilians but this is war
bullets
don't look at your nationality
right an artillery shell follows the
laws of physics it is not a magic shell
that will see oh this person is not
ukrainian or this person is not a not a
soldier so don't don't hurt the person
no that's not how it works
so
when
war happens when there is shelling going
on
sometimes civilians will get hit
especially if the ukrainian government
is putting them as human sheeds which
they have been doing and sometimes the
shells will go in the wrong direction
sometimes there will be crossfire which
will be uncontrolled when two sides are
firing at each other if civilians are
caught in the crossfire they will die so
please understand people use some logic
please use some logic please use some
common sense
i have never said not a single civilian
will die i said the russians will try
their best to minimize civilian
casualties they will try their best to
minimize damage to ukrainian
infrastructure and they will never ever
willingly hurt an indian citizen
okay but if an indian citizen gets
caught in some crossfire that
in that case
we will have a tragic loss of life i
hope it doesn't happen please i do i i
wish and i hope it doesn't happen
and so far the the indian government is
doing a very good job of evacuating the
citizens i hope it is concluded
successfully
but this is war so you
you may have casualties i hope it
doesn't happen but that's how it goes so
i hope that clarifies what i said and i
hope that people will use a little bit
more common sense
while
while understanding things
okay swastika says
russia is claiming that ukraine has
taken indian soul students as hostages
and using them as human shields
uh you can see blatant racism happening
in ukraine
uh mea rejected both claims what do you
think is actually happening how can
india save with students her says am i
biased for thinking ukraine did
absolutely nothing to stop the war and
all that
they are threatening india holding its
students hostage i don't see and and so
on right
so last week i had shown the video of
the ukrainian ambassador to the united
nations
speaking directly to the indian
ambassador and and issuing
a wheeled threat
to the indian
students who were in ukraine and i have
got a lot of flak for that people are
saying you have misinterpreted the words
because he did not say clearly that we
are threatening students obviously he's
a diplomat he will use diplomatic
language especially when he's making a
public threat he will use language that
can be interpreted in a multiple number
of ways but the threat was unmistakable
and whatever he threatened us with they
have actually done it
we know that they have they have been
preventing indian students from leaving
various cities
not allowing indian students to board
trains
also
non-indian foreigners like africans
especially they have been extremely
racist and it's not one or two instances
it's a pattern
it's a big pattern of racism against
indians against africans and again even
against the greek people some some greek
students i believe
that's what i heard yesterday or today
that even greeks were being subjected to
racism so greek people as you know are
not exactly white they are kind of brown
light brown
so there's racism there also
and we know that indians have been kept
in various cities
against their will so that is called
using people as human shields
right so that is precisely what this
individual this thug
the ukrainian ambassador threatened
india with and that's precisely what's
what's happened so i said this
on day two or day three of the war right
and today what i said has been has been
we have seen it in action that's what
they did so they have been using indian
students as hostages they have been in
using indian students as human shields
right
and racism also as we know it's
happening
so that's what the ukraines and
ukrainians have done even the bbc which
is so blatantly and so consistently
anti-india
even the bbc has been forced to report
about this
about the racism that indians are facing
indian students are being beaten are
being beaten up by ukrainians by
ukrainian police even girls are being
beaten up by ukrainian police
we and our students are not being
allowed to board are not being allowed
to get on trains on buses
so what else do you
see except for what i had said that they
are doing they're using indians as
hostages and human shields
that's precisely what we have seen and
uh by now i hope that most of the
indians must have been evacuated the
russians are also uh getting involved
now because they are controlling large
parts of the country so uh i think a
couple of days ago about 48 hours ago
they stopped the war for about six hours
and allowed
indians to be evacuated now the mea
india's ministry of external affairs is
is
still
trying to keep the situation calm
it is
saying we don't know anything about
human shields and hostages that's what
you say when your people
are held as hostages you will try your
best not to antagonize
the hostage takers you will say no no
everything is fine they are very
civilized you will say that until you
get your people out
right
so our people our students are still
in ukraine
i think it out of the 20 000
approximately students at least 18 000
have been evacuated but around 2000 may
still be there
i don't know what is the situation right
now as you speak i hope more have been
evacuated but as long as even one
student
or one citizen is there on ukrainian
soil the mea will try to keep things
very uh
very conciliatory and not try to and try
their best not to offend the ukrainians
because the lives of our citizens are at
stake once everything is over we will
issue whatever statement which whichever
factual statement we need to issue
okay rahul says the unbiased news
channels keep blaming russia for their
unprovoked attack on a sovereign nation
and that nothing can justify this
do putin's actions violate the buddha
pest memorandum
that they would respect the sovereignty
of ukraine and does it mean the treaties
and agreements amount to nothing in
today's world
and quinn reverend says indians are in
no place to criticize sensible and
restrained u.s foreign policies i love
that sensible and you restrained u.s
foreign policy
if the u.s got militarily involved in
you in europe it would start a world war
then you'd be calling the us an
aggressor an escalator
if the u.s does nothing then you will
score it on your high horse if the u.s
did anything more you would scold in
again and so on so forth so india until
india has a clear position sit down this
is what this most likely american
gentleman is saying if sensible and
restrained foreign policy okay first of
all when it comes to treaties and
agreements
remember the iranians and the americans
etc and some of the countries that they
had the iran nuclear deal an agreement
that was signed and ratified
and the americans just
walked away from it right
they tore the treaty into pieces so
whenever they want they can tear a
treaty into pieces they can tear it to
threads they can walk away from a treaty
unilaterally
so then what is the meaning of a treaty
in today's world zero right the chinese
had this treaty with the uh
with the uk that they would have one
country two systems with fun with
respect to hong kong they walked away
from the treaty unilaterally
so it's this is how it works when you
are strong
you can do whatever you like you can set
the rules you can break the rules when
you are weak you have to follow the
rules you have to obey the rules which
are set by the strong the strong powers
will keep changing the rules whenever
they wish as they wish to suit
themselves and the weak countries have
to keep following the rules even when
the rules keep changing that is the way
geopolitics worlds works that's the way
the world works
so treaties and agreements actually mean
nothing the strong countries can
change
the set of rules in it and they won't
they can break a treaty anytime they
wish right now
they they have been saying that the
russian attack
the russian intervention in ukraine has
been an unprovoked attack right
so let's let's understand do we have a
map somewhere let's take a look at the
map yeah it's always nice to see the map
so
let me share the map with you in order
to explain what is happening
where's the map where's the map here's
the map let me remove the question
and let's take a look at the map
so this is the map now let's take a look
at
europe
so there is this
organization
or coalition or whatever you want to
call it called nato
north atlantic treaty organization which
is essentially
led by the us all right and
in 1990 until 1990 nato
had 16 members mostly
uh nations that are in western europe
okay western europe uk france germany
and so on so forth these were members of
nato the objective of nato was to
counter balance the ussr so it was an
anti-ussr
military alliance
that's what nato was in until 1990 nato
had 16 members in february 1990 the then
ussr
facilitated the facilitated the
reunification of east and west germany
in exchange for an american guarantee
that nato would not expand even one inch
eastward
okay so this guarantee was issued to the
ussr by the americans in february 1990.
and the german reunification happened
the ussr broke up and the the successor
state was russia
to whom the guarantee still applied
in 1999 poland hungary and the czech
republic became members of nato so the
promise was broken the guarantee was
broken in 2004 another bunch of
countries bulgaria estonia latvia
lithuania romania slovakia slovenia this
entire bunch of countries became part of
nato again the promise was broken in
2009 albania and croatia became members
of nato in 2017 montenegro and north
macedonia became members of nato and now
we have countries like
bosnia-herzegovina georgia ukraine that
have been promised nato membership
ukraine especially becomes a very big
problem because it is right on the
doorstep
of russia
right in other countries too so what it
essentially means is that you will have
new u.s nuclear weapons on russia's
doorstep now imagine if russia were to
place
russian nuclear weapons in canada and in
mexico on american borders on the
american border or in cuba which
happened in the 1960s how would the
americans react violently
but it's okay for them to do it on the
russian
threshold
to to essentially encircle russia so
these are deliberate
repeated provocations by nato by the us
and eventually it became too much for
russia to ignore because that would
essentially put them at enormous threat
right so
so mr putin in the initial days of his
tenure as the president of the of russia
he had even
considered applying for nato membership
it did not work out and you can see what
has been the consequences of of the
of subsequent developments right so when
you talk about uh
what was the term this this gentleman
used
the sensible and restrained foreign
policy are you kidding
sensible and restrained foreign policy
are you kidding who are you kidding
this is incredibly provocative foreign
policy
right
that the
and when you talk about restraint and
all that where was the restraint in
baghdad there was a restraint in iraq
how many people died as a result of the
u.s invasion of iraq at least two
million
how many
innocent afghans died
at least a hundred thousand i would say
i don't have the exact number so you can
look it up but
very large numbers how many
innocent civilians died in libya
at least 10 000 minimum
so you call this sensible and restrained
foreign policy
who are you guys kidding
right
so that's what i can say that's what i
can that's the information that is
available everywhere this is well known
i mean there's no controversy here these
are just facts
so
so it all depends on when you start your
clock
see the way you look at history depends
on how on what time period what slice of
time you're looking at if you start your
clock
in
in late february 2022 then it looks like
the russians have suddenly launched an
unprovoked
attack on ukraine
right that's how it looks
but then if you look if you go back to
2014 then you will see that the
americans have affected an illegal
unconstitutional regime change in
ukraine
and installed a puppet government so if
you look at the if you start the clock
in 2014 that's what you see if you start
the clock in 1991 or 1990 when the
americans gave a guarantee
that they would not expand nato and then
it was broken repeatedly then you will
see a whole different picture and if you
go back further in time and i've spoken
about the history of the of the
of the slavic people and the russian
people you will see that ukraine is an
artificial nation
there is
it has never it's always been russian
territory throughout history throughout
the past 1000 years since the beginning
of these uh the
the history of the kievan ruse people
right
with prince rurik prince oleg prince
volodymyr and so on so forth so in the
previous one of the previous live
streams i've given i've gone into the
details of this history if you can look
and look you can look it up
so
if you want to have a very narrow myopic
view of history then you will it will
look like russians have launched an
unprovoked attack on ukraine but if you
look at the proper context you will
understand that there are reasons why
this happened the russians were backed
into a corner and they were given no
choice at the end when all the options
ran out they had to do this
so that's
what
the facts tell us
okay next question
uh sultan verma says as you said
the war was necessary for russia i had a
debate on this with my elder brother he
was saying if russia had kept the army
at the border the pressure would be the
same on ukraine
uh what would be the other scenario if
the russians kept their army at the
border
and the other question is how will putin
justify to russia the invasion was
inevitable
uh putin is solely blamed as if it was
his madness to invade ukraine
uh was war the only solution
okay so let's say that so the first
question is what if the russians had
only kept the
the army at the borders then then would
all the problems be resolved no then
ukraine would have a legitimate reason
for joining nato and the americans would
have sent troops and maybe further
provocations would have ensued
and the regime would not have changed in
ukraine the regime that was illegally
illegitimately unconstitutionally put in
place in 2014 in the
nato-led coup would have stayed in place
and therefore the objective which is
regime change would never have been
achieved it's still not achieved as of
today 10 days into the intervention but
i suppose it will happen in the next 10
days or so so
so yes so going to war was necessary in
order to effect the regime change in in
order to demilitarize and denazify
ukraine
without the military intervention those
things would not have happened it's
still a work in progress
but yes so the war was necessary just
keeping the army on the borders of
ukraine would not have solved these
problems
that mr putin seeks to resolve
right
so the region change would not have
happened ukraine would not have been
demilitarized and ukraine would
certainly not have been denatified
so those three objectives could never
have been achieved by keeping the
russian army on the borders of ukraine
it needed a proper military intervention
uh now the other question is was what
the only solution how will putin
justify to the russians that the
invasion was inevitable i just laid out
the entire history of the
of of the of the matter the russians
were given a guarantee by the americans
in february 1990 that nato would not
expand a single inch eastward and they
have broken that guarantee repeatedly
1999 2004 2009 2017 and then into it in
2021 22 again the provocations continued
ukraine could have become a member of
nato bosnia herzegovina and georgia also
these are incredibly grave provocations
they are encircling russia this is um
this essentially is is a matter of life
and death for russia for at this point
so the
invasion the military intervention can
be justified can be
clearly justified if you put it into the
right context in in the in the
in the context of the
never-ending
eastward expansion of nato in breach of
the guarantee that the russians were
given so that justifies what mr putin
has done
that's the russian view
dewan says
why 90 percent of the western media is
showing that putin is doing what what
putin is doing is completely wrong they
are portraying him as a sinister villain
people in russia are also protesting
even though it's their own national
interest
see
there is there is a whole propaganda war
that is fought in addition to the war
that's fought on the ground and the
propaganda war is fought on social media
with the various
establishment mainstream media outlets
washington post new york times the the
british bbc the guardian and all the
various nato member countries whatever
outlets they have whether it is german
outlets or french outlets or whatever so
there's this whole propaganda war that
is fought to keep up the morale of the
people and to make them feel that the
their
that the ukrainians are winning or
whatever
and in order
to justify the sanctions you're imposing
on the on on russia
and whatever future actions you want to
take against russia you have to portray
them as evil as villains and you to
portray their leader mr putin is a crazy
madman he's gone mad
he's gone completely mad they're
comparing him with either adolf hitler
these days
right they are even comparing him with
ching is khan they are saying
that he's asian now he is so bad that
he's not even european anymore he's
asian
so it's all about demonizing somebody
when you demonize somebody it makes it
very easy for you
to
uh
to do any kind of further action that
you want against them
so if you want to brutalize a country
you have to first demonize it if you
want to oppress a certain class of
people you have to first demonize them
there is classic
marxist strategy it is textbook marxist
strategy
right collective guilt so that's a whole
different story but that's the reason
why it is being done so they are
portraying mr putin as a
hitler-like person or a chingus khan
like person as a crazy madman he's gone
mad he's completely unrestrained he's
lost his marbles that's what they're
doing so that is the justice that is
going to lay the groundwork for and the
justification for any action they take
in the future
that's what is happening
chi-ching says we can see that most of
the civilians of ukraine old and young
are joining the military to stop to stop
the russian troops
is this a sign that that russia may may
lose the war
so you are right teaching the uh the i
would not say all of them or most of
them are joining the the war effort but
the ukrainian government has released
lots of prisoners criminals and given
them weapons they are also issuing
ak-47s and various other rifles
automatic rifles machine guns molotov
cocktails bombs etc to civilians
right so they are doing that too
now and let's understand
what this means
the job of defending the country
is that of the professional armed forces
it is their job to do it
now when you are forced
to start arming your civilians what does
it mean
it means that your professional armed
forces are no longer able to do the job
of defending the country and therefore
civilians need to be enlisted
so it actually is an act of utter
desperation
if you are forced to start arming the
civilians
it means that you are losing the war it
doesn't mean the russians are losing the
war it means the ukrainians are
desperate they may lose the war and the
other reason why they're arming
civilians
it's a very cynical thing to do
is to to have more civilian casualties
see if you if the russians the russians
have been instructed not to deliberately
harm any civilians and we are seeing the
evidence of that on lots of video clips
that are circulating they are not
harming civilians in the face of all
kinds of protests and provocations
but imagine the russian soldiers come
face to face with a person who is
holding a gun
in that case they have to treat that
person as an enemy combatant
they have no other option
when you come acro when a soldier when a
professionally trained soldier comes
face to face with a person holding a
weapon
they are
compelled to treat that person as an
enemy combatant
and then what will happen is you will
have civilian casualties and that is
great for media propaganda the russians
are killing civilians there are so many
civilians who died
so that is a very cynical and sinister
and diabolical thing to do to arm
civilians who have no training in using
weapons you can't learn how to use an
ak-47 with half an hour or two days of
training
you need a proper training core that
that lasts weeks
okay weapon these
weapons are extremely dangerous things
you can hurt yourself you can hurt your
for you the civilian population if you
don't know how to use it and you can't
learn how to use it in half an hour or
even two days
so
so that's what's happening
so if civilians are joining the war
effort it means that the ukrainians are
desperate and they are losing and they
are trying to create unnecessary
civilian casualties
in order to win the propaganda war
ahan says do you think vladimir putin
will make viktor yanukovich as the new
president of ukraine
and also why has apart from russia not a
single country criticized the genocide
in donbas
so
it doesn't matter who is installed as
the new president of ukraine it will be
somebody who will be favorably disposed
towards russia it could be mr yanukovych
or some other puppet president there's
no other way of looking at it it's going
to be puppet it's going to be a person
who will report will be absolutely 100
loyal to mr putin
that's just how it goes that is
the brutal truth
of geopolitics right you install puppet
governments
so the the
other question is apart from russia why
has nobody criticized the genocide in
donbas that has not been reported at all
there has been a war going on in the
donbas region
of eastern ukraine since 2014
and there have been all kinds of
atrocities that have been perpetrated on
the russian-speaking people of this
region by various ukrainian armed
militias whether it's the regular armed
forces or the various
neo-nazi
militias
and yeah you could consider it to be
genocide definitely
and the west has deliberately ignored
that the west has a track record of
selectively reporting things and
selectively ignoring certain things
we know what's been happening in tibet
since the 1950s
a proper genocide
does the west ever talk about it they
talk about the yui gurus
the uighurs are very convenient these
days as a state to beat china with but
why has the west never spoken about
tibet
because it doesn't want to
why does the west not speak about the
genocide that's happening in yemen right
now
who is doing it by the way find out
there's a genocide happening in yemen
right now civilians are being bombarded
from the skies
and they don't speak about it most of
you may not even know about the fact
that this is happening right now as we
speak
right and similarly the genocide in
donbass has never been reported upon
nobody even knows that it happened so
this
is the true face of the western media
the mainstream media even the indian
media by the way
all right so there are certain indian
news channels that are
these days they are reporting
the ukraine uh
war
24x7
right
there are two or three channels that are
doing that unfortunately
i will not take names of the names of
the channels but the reporting is from a
western perspective it's not from the
indian perspective
it is completely
biased towards the nato perspective
so we don't have an indian perspective
at all in the indian media they are
simply puppets of the west
that's what we are seeing some of these
media channels i am told are trying to
tone down that by that that very visible
tilt towards the west and try to be a
little bit more balanced
but it's it's not really working
so that's what you see right so that's
that's the truth about the media they
will report
their reporting is biased it is
selective and they omit whatever is not
convenient
uh herschel says mr putin has already
ordered to activate the nuclear command
if it really happens then how will the
world react and so on
and reports came out that
that russia already used a vacuum bomb
which is a violation of the geneva
convention
again these so-called reports come out
in on social media in various western
media outlets what is the evidence that
the russians use a vacuum bomb it's it's
called a thermobaric bomb by the way
okay so uh what's the evidence the
russians have used this for this sort of
weapon there's no evidence beyond the
claims the empty claims made by various
propaganda propaganda outlets there is
no verifiable evidence that this sort of
weapon has been used which is a
violation of whatever convention geneva
convention or whatever right
so there's no evidence it's just wild
claims that they are making to further
demonize the russians
uh they also made claims of the russians
using cluster bombs cluster weapons
which
again has is completely unproven
now the americans the nato people the
nato armed forces used cluster bombs
cluster munitions
during their
genocide
or let's call it intervention or
liberation of yugoslavia in albania in
kosovo
civilians lots and lots of civilians
died in that lots of people lost limbs
in that
where what happened to the geneva
convention there or maybe at that time
cluster cluster munitions were not part
of the geneva convention i'm not really
sure what exactly it is but we know for
a fact there is documentary evidence
horrific images i will not share them
here but it's known they use cluster
weapons custom munitions in
on civilians so when they do it it's
fine when russians do it even though we
don't have any evidence they've done it
then it's bad
so the same things they have done
do you want to accuse the the russians
of doing it and then demonize them
look at the hypocrisy right
as far as the nuclear command goes mr
putin has ordered them to be on high
alert which is just a way of telling the
west stay away he obviously nobody wants
to use nuclear weapons unless there is
no
uh unless that you have you have run out
of options well the russians have not by
any means run out of any options it's
just
a way of of uh
telling the us and nato stay back we are
serious we're not messing around here
that's all it is
uh priyanka says while russia continues
attacking ukraine destroying cities one
by one
lots of people lots of countries around
the world are putting sanctions against
it and various companies are terminating
businesses with them how long could it
take for either country to give up
okay priyanka i would i'm wondering
which city has been destroyed
see see the thing is this
even in the indian media they will have
this i remember during the
so-called
anti-caa protests
there was this
one protest that was going on like 15
people were protesting with some play
cards and banners in there these drums
and they were doing playing the drums
and all that
so 15 people are protesting and there
are 50 cameras around them and they are
portraying this as a national nationwide
protest
they manufactured this this entire
narrative
in this manner 15 20 people protesting
somewhere and 50 cameras around them and
all the media channels are reporting it
24x7 as if some huge protest is
happening throughout the country these
were all
artificial
astroturf protests but they were
portrayed
as nationwide spontaneous protests now
once again in ukraine we are seeing
these various reports various clips on
the internet on social media of this
building destroyed here in that building
destroyed there and some some
city block that is damaged and all that
and these selective
clips
are being used to portray
uh to to create the impression that the
the the russians are destroying entire
cities that is simply not the case the
russians are doing their best not to
damage any civilian infrastructure the
electricity is still running everywhere
the internet is still running everywhere
all telecommunications are working fine
buses are flying
trains are running
so there is no i mean it's a complete
lie that the russians are destroying
cities one by one not a single city has
been destroyed
yeah there have been some there has been
some damage to some buildings they have
taken out certain buildings with uh
targeted strikes such as one of the
buildings in which the azov neo-nazi
division had their headquarters that was
taken out and in case the ukrainians are
shelling the russians
from within an apartment complex they
will have to retaliate right so
so some damage will happen but there's
by no means destroying cities one by one
that's simply not the case but that's
the impression they are trying to create
on social media and in the mainstream
media so these are just lies it's just
propaganda it is designed to turn
people's opinion against
russia and in favor of nato
that's just the propaganda war that we
are witnessing and it's very easy to
mislead people by with this
now the sanctions and all that
various companies terminating business
how long
will it take for either country to give
up the russia the ukrainians
see
i see i foresee the
military objectives of the russian
intervention
being met within the next 10 days that's
what i foresee so today is the 5th of
march i
foresee
i believe that by the 15th of march
most of the military objectives of the
russian intervention in ukraine will be
achieved that's what i think i know it's
a fool's errand to make predictions
but let me just put a prediction out
there
i know how it feel i i
i know
i have experienced this myself firsthand
that i make a prediction and then i
look foolish but here let me let me go
again so i think in the next 10 days the
military objectives will be achieved now
the sanctions
have been put on russia we know that
they have dumped every possible sanction
on russia they have essentially given
russia nothing more to lose
that's so that what they've done
right
so they have essentially told putin that
no matter i mean you can now go and
conquer poland if you want and there's
no more sanctions we can throw on you
because we've already thrown everything
at you the entire kitchen sink
and russia is not going to give up
because of the sanctions
mr putin
has been planning this i believe since
for at least 10 years
right
so it was not done 10 years ago because
the the right to the right pieces on the
chessboard were not in place
so planning an invasion like this an
operation like this takes time it has to
be done meticulously so i believe the
planning has been has been in pro
progress for at least 10 years
so all of these steps that the western
nations have taken
that the u.s has taken essentially
have been foreseen
all of these calculations would have
been all of these things would have been
calculated and taken into account when
looking at the pros and cons of of
launching an operation like this so
there is no surprise that mr putin has
faced he would have known that all these
sanctions would be placed on russia the
swift thing would be cut off and
whatever else so he has anticipated this
he's prepared for it
and there's a bigger
a bigger reconfiguration of the world
order that is in process right now
uh uh how should russia counter the fake
news and one-sided reporting favoring
ukraine the social media popular news
channels are largely under the influence
of nato countries especially the us
failure to do so may lead to massive
civil protests and so on so forth
so how should russia counter the fake
news the russians are already countering
the fake news they have banned facebook
they have been they have blocked access
to facebook and russia and they may go
ahead and do the same with other social
media channels outlets as well
instagram twitter
whatever else right
so they can do it the chinese have their
own firewall the great firewall of china
and they don't allow any any us
social media to info to make its way
into china we know that the chinese
citizens use vpn to
to bypass these restrictions and the
chinese government kind of tolerates it
to some extent
but they could also crack down on such
such violations so the russians have
banned facebook they may soon ban bbc
cnn all that
all of those
media networks as well so these are some
of the ways in which the russians can do
it
and the thing is that the russian
citizens are not that that easy to
mislead
okay this is interesting
so the question is
uh what anurag says what impact of this
war will be on india
we saw many western diplomats are
unhappy with the indian decision to
abstain from voting at the un security
council they just says why did no one
condemn u.s and nato for abandoning
ukraine but everybody is showing their
discomfort and displeasure at india not
supporting ukraine when did we become so
important for them
and anonymous says what will be the
consequences for india after this war is
the west is pissed off with us and
how should we prepare for it very good
questions
so the question is
why is the west suddenly blaming india
and what are the consequences what is
going to be the impact of all of this on
india very good question let me uh
share my screen
and uh
one second
so let's let's take a look at what the
uh what the chatter is on social media
so so various uh commentators diplomats
uh think tank experts analysts etc
from the west are
chattering on social media
and putting out this message
about india so this is a guy called
robert shrimsley he's saying india's
substantial is a useful wake-up call to
those in the west talking it up as part
of the alliance of democratic countries
they want to build so he is saying india
is not a democratic country it's a
wake-up call for the west
edward lewis says whatever the
calculations misplace loyalties etc
india is at risk of abdicating its
respect its respect is one of the
world's leading democracies
so he's saying india is losing respect
this individual derek grossman says
india abstains again
icky stuff really icky stuff so india is
icky now not clean dirty
and apple bomb says it is shameful that
india abstained and somebody else says
that in india in particular is going to
have to face some extremely tough
reprisals from the west you don't get to
do this and then ask for western support
when pakistan messes in kashmir or china
encroaches on the northern border
this guy says that
india and pakistan could hang their
heads in shame and not receive a single
penny piece and aid from the uk as if
they are giving us any any aid they have
stolen trillions of dollars worth of
money from us but they're what they're
talking about so-called aid
alex vikram says western leaders are
furious at modi over his support for
putin for for putin
jeff smith says
that we i can't sympathize with indian
commentators gleefully spouting russian
propaganda and cheering on putin you
took the wrong pill comrades
bruno the great bruno says
india
fully aligning with russia the it's a gl
it's a great blemish for
the country for india
ben bruno says that uh
a question was very simple but dr s
jayshankar stumbled and mumbled
uh i guess we now know that for india in
territorial integrity is something that
applies only to india so that sort of uh
chatter is going on in the west and
there's a reason for this
they are trying to portray india is a
country that is undemocratic it is a
fascist country and it is a country that
that supports military aggression and a
country that supports russia it does not
support democracy it's an undemocratic
fascist evil oppressive
and all that kind of country
that's what that's the impression they
are trying to create on social media
what is the reason for that
they are building
the justification
for not supporting india in the future
in supporting india and what
supporting india against
a future
chinese aggression
the americans
are anticipating
that china is going to
attack india in some way in the coming
future not very far future coming future
see everyone is everyone believe that
the chinese will try to take taiwan
right now that's not going to happen
taiwan is too too big a problem for them
right now they are not in a position to
take taiwan because the taiwanese are
well prepared and it will be a red line
the america americans will not allow the
the chinese to cross
so what can china do china can attack
india
and the americans are anticipating that
and they don't want to get involved in
this they don't want to help india so
that right now they are creating the
groundwork they are preparing they are
laying the groundwork on social media
they are creating the justification for
their people for the citizens
because see if china attacks democratic
india
and the americans don't help india it
looks bad because all america always
talks about democracy democracy
democracy and india is the world's
biggest democracy so democracies are
supposed to help each other and if the
americans don't do it the the public may
not like it
so
they are now trying to
portray india as an undemocratic
fascist evil oppressive icky kind of
country
so that's what we are seeing on social
media right now so it looks like the
americans are anticipating
a conflict between india and china soon
so that's what i had tweeted
recently
like
like yesterday i said that india needs
to prepare for a short sharp 1962 like
conflict with china could happen before
24 or in 2024 the objective would be to
inflict a military defeat on india
to
to break off the northeast to cut off
india's access to its northeast
and that would cause the current
government
of prime minister modi to lose the 2024
election election if you if you lose a
big piece of territory the people will
vote you out of power right
and all indications are that the u.s
anticipates this india must be ready
that's what i said and
in response to that willingness
who has appeared on my podcast in on
this channel she said that she
anticipates military tensions between
china and india ahead of
september 2022 as xi jinping is
dedicated to solidifying his power and
will need the strong support of his
military hawks to do that taiwan is not
an option so it will likely affect india
so she anticipates
some sort of conflict
before september this year
i said it will happen before or in 2024
and it looks like
the chinese
desire regime change in india
and even the americans seem to desire
regime change in india nobody wants a
strong assertive government in india
they want a weak
pliable government in india and narendra
modi's government is not a weak and
pliable government so the americans
don't want that even the chinese don't
want that so it's a paradox that the
americans and chinese both seem to
desire
a change of government a change of
regime in india and the best way to do
that would for would be for china to
attack india break off a part of india's
territory and that would be a
humiliation for india like 1962 and the
government will lose power in the next
elections
so that seems to be what we are
witnessing
right now
and because of that to to prepare the
groundwork and the justification for not
helping india
we are seeing all of this
this this big campaign on social media
whose objective is to demonize india as
an undemocratic
fascist
evil country that's what we're
witnessing
so we need to be prepared india needs to
be prepared for
a conflict with china in the short to
medium term
okay
so the the logical question to that is
will russia help india if china starts a
war
and what's the probability of india
defeating china vedic says
if there's a war between india and china
or india pakistan will
will the russians support us by any
means one says can the chinese also do
the same to us what russia is doing with
ukraine
is china supposedly has entered parts of
arunachal pradesh can china do the same
with us
so in the current scenario in the
current situation the russians are in no
position to help india
if there is a conflict between india and
china they are not in a position to do
that they are not strong enough to do
that they are
they need the support of the
chinese especially the financial support
they are trying to create a different
global order
so the world is becoming more and more
bipolar right now
so they are trying to create a different
system
and they are trying to break free of the
american system so the russians and the
chinese need each other's support
so if there is a war between india and
china the russians are not in a position
to help india
the question also is that can the
chinese do the same to us what russia is
doing with ukraine
so is india prepared for this
eventuality of a short sharp 1962 like
war with china
i believe india is very well prepared
for that
i think it would be really foolish for
the chinese
to believe that they can indulge in some
sort of misadventure with india
if they were to do it they would most
likely
aim for the siliguri corridor the
chicken's neck which connects
the far east of india which we call
which we call the northeast with the
so-called mainland of india
so the chinese may try to aim for that
and try to cut that off
so can the chinese succeed in that i
think it would be really stupid of the
chinese to try such a thing because i
think india is really well prepared if
the chinese do that india can take the
fight into chinese occupied tibet
territory india can take out all the
chinese military bases we have the
missiles that can do it our missiles are
more or less unstoppable and we can fire
salvos of missiles we can even send our
fighter aircraft and we have an
advantage when it comes to the air force
because the chinese air force in tibet
is the planes are at a very are
stationed at a very high altitude which
means they can carry less less fuel and
less weaponry whereas our planes can
carry much more weaponry and much more
fuel so we have a significant advantage
there
and i think india
would anticipate this sort of
potential
misadventure for the chinese so i think
india is very well prepared i don't
think the chinese would succeed if they
try this they may end up losing more
than
more than
they can they would gain
right
and it could end up essentially
humiliating the chinese leadership which
would be a disaster in china
the chinese
don't tolerate humiliation
humiliation in the in a in a military
encounter
inevitably leads to regime change in
china so i think it would be playing
with final with fire if the chinese
tried that i think india is very well
prepared
and of course we have certain red lines
the chinese will not even dare to cross
because we have the ultimate weapon also
so i think india is reasonably well
prepared but we must never
never
be complacent we have to be well
prepared at all times
especially now when things are changing
really fast
okay
uh ankit boy says
the rule the rule based world order in
the international organizations are they
all myths of western hegemony under the
u.s events like the nato intervention in
the kosovo war iraq invasion and
countless other events tell us that
western powers bend the rules according
to their interests and when somebody
else does that these countries and
organizations become hyperactive
conscience says please elaborate on all
the incidents when where the u.s invaded
other nations
in the name of liberation and no
international organization questioned
their actions good question
i have some data here
so these are u.s interventions since the
second world war
from the 1940s all the way into the
2020s china syria korea china iran
guatemala tibet indonesia cuba
congo dominican republic vietnam so on
and so forth so many interventions
and yet it does not mention here the
intervention the invasion
of yemen the genocide that's happening
in yemen as we speak it also doesn't
talk about the
the u.s financing of pakistani terrorism
in india for two three decades
it doesn't that is also not mentioned
here
the americans financed
pakistani terrorism in india from the
1980s onwards
we know what happened in kashmir right
the
ethnic cleansing of the kashmiri hindus
in
1989 1991
so all of that was financed by the
americans who else was financing the
pakistanis
they were essentially that we are giving
the money to pakistan and arms and
ammunition to pakistan
to end terrorism
in pakistan and to defeat the soviets in
afghanistan to defeat terrorists you
don't need to give a nation f-16s and
fighter planes but that's what they did
they always knew that these planes would
be used against india and they were fine
with that so the americans financed
pakistani terrorism in india and so much
more so these are some of the
interventions that the americans have
done across the world so the so called
rules-based world order it is a fairy
tale
it's a myth
when they do it it's perfectly fine if
somebody else does it it's a terrible
sin and you need to dump sanctions on
that country
so that's the thing right so when you
are the most powerful country in the
world you make the rules and you break
the rules whenever you feel and nobody
is going to question you that's how it
works but now
now
things are changing
you can see on even the mainstream media
channels everybody is calling out the
hypocrisy
and the track record
okay next question raj paul says
[Laughter]
funny funny funny you still believe that
the the us will help taiwan
the u.s is
eu is only interested in selling arms
japan needs to revise their policy eu
should be an alert abhijit singh says
there is no defense treaty between the
u.s and taiwan u.s state department is
officially state blah blah blah it will
give weapons to defending itself
understand something my friends
the u.s cannot afford to lose taiwan to
the chinese the u.s simply can't afford
to have that
if the chinese gain taiwan it gives them
access to the entire indo-pacific it
will be the end of american hegemony in
the indo-pacific that's what it means
it is a frontier that the americans
cannot afford to lose they cannot afford
to allow the chinese to breach that
frontier the island chains there are two
island chains if you look at the map
uh let's let's go and look at the map
um one second
not this sorry
not this
i have to bring in the map
just a second
here's the map
let me remove the question so you can
see it properly this is the map so there
are two island chains
so one
so as you can see the chinese are
encircled at sea
over here you have the japanese you have
the japanese islands
if you go down south you nava
and so on
here you have taiwan
and here you have the philippines
indonesia and so on
so it is encircled by all these islands
and these islands the forces that are
stationed there are essentially not very
friendly to the chinese
the japanese are essentially
uh
they they are in
they are under the
they there's no nice way of putting it
japan is essentially under u.s
occupation right now right it has been
that way since the end of the second
world war
taiwan is a de facto american client
state
the philippines have traditionally been
very much pro-us
and so on so all of these i this entire
island chain it encircles china and
keeps chinese actions limited due to
a certain geographical territory of the
of the ocean
so if the chinese were to gain taiwan
they could
break free of these shackles
and they would be free to
to rule
if they can the indo-pacific region if
taiwan forced they would also be free to
make their way into the indian ocean
and to outnumber the indian army and
possibly try to outmatch the indian navy
in the indian ocean so taiwan is key to
that the americans cannot afford to lose
taiwan right so no matter what you say
that the americans don't have a treaty
or whatever they will simply not allow
the chinese to take taiwan it is going
to be a disaster for the us it will be
the end of america's superpower status
if the chinese
succeed in conquering taiwan
and that's why you will say that the
americans have significant amount
of
of presence of forces of strength of
weapons and all that in on taiwanese
soil
so
it is still not time it is the the
chinese are still not in a position to
make a move on taiwan and that's why i
was saying saying that they could try to
make a move on india if they if they
feel that they can
get away with that
okay spurs says the removal of certain
russian banks from swift
shows how the global interdependence can
be weaponized by the west
does this mean that india should invest
more in self-reliant sources of fuel
like solar wind hydro etc
as in the future our dependence on the
middle east and others for oil and coal
could also be weaponized how else can we
hedge risks to our energy security very
good question india needs to diversify
its sources of energy
so
buy energy by
buy fuel from as many countries as
possible diversify your portfolio
and as we know
even the uae has abstained again in this
vote against the russians
during the current ongoing crisis so the
uae is also abstained so it's not
playing
per the american playbook
and india and the uae have excellent
relations so that's one of the sources
of our energy security india and saudi
arabia also have good very good
relations and we should try and acquire
other sources of energy as well and like
you said we should also try and
diversify into solar wind hydro and all
that
as of today we need hydrocarbons
we need fossil fuels you cannot
uh fly a fighter jet based on solar
energy right as of today the technology
still doesn't exist if you have a navy
if you have submarines you can have
nuclear submarines for sure but most of
the most of your vessels your ships
are going to use
fossil fuels so and and the entire
automobile system and everything in
india most of it is based on fossil
fuels and that's that's the case all
around the world right now
so as of right now we need to ensure
that we diversify our sources of fossil
fuels
that's what we should do and in the
future as more tech as technologies
evolve and get better
we can
diversify in other things as well
so yes you're right we need to be
mindful of this that everything can be
weaponized the finite the global
financial system can be weaponized the
uh
fuels
energy can be weaponized everything can
be weaponized especially when you have
one country controlling everything so
india needs to be mindful of that and
india needs to diversify as far as it as
it can
nishan says can upi replace swift as
some countries have started adopting it
and swastika says can the swift be
replaced by india india's upi to counter
western economic hegemony
so what is swift swift is a means of
transferring money from one bank to
another from one country to another
it's essentially a private
uh
company i believe that charges money for
all the transactions that you do
so swift
can be replaced it's not very hard to
create a swift-like system in india in
china in russia in some other country
the main problem is to is to get lots of
other countries to adopt this system
that's the main thing so right now swift
is controlled by the west
when we say west we essentially mean the
us
and that's why they're able to cut off
any country that they don't they don't
like from the system
so even without swift the russians will
be able to do financial transactions but
it will be an additional hardship
because swift makes things very
convenient
so india could create its own swift or
the chinese could create their own
swiftlike system
or
what about the upi right the upi is not
exactly a swift light system it's a
different kind of system but you could
enhance the upi
system and
and bring it into the the the kind of
ability or capabilities that swift has
it's certainly something india can do
the only thing is how many countries can
you get to adopt this system and if you
do that
obviously the americans will not like it
because you're trying to create a
parallel system
so india has to consider all these
things
right now we are still not strong enough
to stand up to the eu to the us we are
still a small
three trillion dollar economy right so
india has has to wait india has to work
hard india has to bide its time
india has to
right now keep its head down not try and
antagonize the big powers
and build up its economy to at least
the level of 10 trillion dollars
so the the
replacement for swift can be created
it's not very hard to do that
okay prager says as a data scientist i
can claim that creating a web browser
environment is probably the most
difficult it task
as it requires huge resources given the
current scenario of ukraine russia
and the way google and apple have
restricted russian access
it is imperative that we create our own
web browser and search engine as
effective as google
how can we make that happen
is any government or private
organization working on it as far as i
know
nobody seems to be working on such a
thing you are absolutely right
see right now we i hear that microsoft
has announced that it will no longer
support um
that it will no longer support its
operations in russia so windows updates
will not happen if you are in russia and
if you have a windows laptop or computer
and so on so forth they're cutting off
all
all support
so that could lead to problems
right
and uh
so it is it is useful to have your own
systems your own infrastructure
your own like you said web browser
environment your own search engines and
all that the chinese have done that they
have their own search engine they have
their own social media
the russians also have their own search
engine
uh i don't remember what it's called
they don't have their own social media
but they don't they may not need it or
they may be they may be in a position to
develop it so i think in the future
all big countries all powerful countries
will become more and more mindful of the
fact that these things can be weaponized
and all countries will start creating
their own social media their own search
engine
and you will find
the compartmentalization
of the internet
coming into the picture
the chinese already have it
the so-called great fire wall of china
in the future any country that that
wishes to remain a sovereign nation may
be forced
to implement something like that because
it's very easy to manufacture public
opinion using social media
very easy it's very easy to to influence
elections
in a democratic country from abroad
using social media
right
so it's it's a big problem so i
you're right this is very important for
india
especially if india wants to remain as a
sovereign nation
an independent nation
in the in the third decade of the 21st
century so india needs to have its own
search engine in india needs to have
i mean there's nobody in india that
manufactures laptops or computers right
we
are planning to become a big
manufacturer of semiconductors and chips
it's still something that's just a plan
it's not been implemented yet i hope it
happens quickly in the next decade so
that will make india independent from
other countries
in that regard in that respect but
it is also very important for india to
have its own search engines
not one multiple
and its own social media
and all of that maybe its own operating
system as well
so all of this needs to happen as far as
i know i am not aware of any
private company or government
organization that's doing it
but i hope it happens so you have raised
a very important
point here
okay a bunch of questions about the
win-lose scenarios what happens if what
what happens to india if russia wins
what happens to india's interests if
russia loses right
um
so what happens in both cases is what
all these questions are asking
kamleshwar krishna singh says what will
happen to india's geopolitical
perspective if russia wins or loses the
war
greetings from amsterdam greetings sir
and so on so what happens
see most likely russia is winning no
matter what they say on social media as
i showed you on the maps
russia is most likely going to achieve
its military objectives
in the next 10 days it looks like that
so if russia wins it secures
its possession of ukraine
then the global order changes
because uh
the the nato will not be able to expand
that far
and other countries may also be mindful
of the power of russia and they may
try to
try to strike a balance between nato and
russia countries like poland and the
various baltic republics and so on so
forth
so that would place russia in a more
powerful
position it would also
bolster china's geopolitical ambitions
right
so what does it mean for india
see the thing is this
let's say russia loses they lose the war
in ukraine
they are beaten back
that sort of thing is terrible mr puti
if that happens mr putin may lose his
presidency also somebody else may come
into the picture because russians don't
tolerate failure mostly
so russia would then become a very weak
country crippled by sanctions and so on
in that case it's bad for india why is
that because india needs russia as a
counterweight to china
right now the russians and the chinese
are cooperating
but let me assure you it's not a long
term cooperation
if you look at the map
you will see what i mean
where's the map
look at
russia
look at china
they have a very long shared border
and when you have a shared border and
you are both powerful countries that is
geopolitical
i mean that is a recipe for the
geopolitical conflict
when you have two powerful nations
who have a shared long shared common
border there is going to erupt into
conflict at some time or the other so in
the long run russia and
in china are geopolitical adversaries
right now
they are cooperating
because it is convenient for them to
cooperate
so for india
it is good to have a more a strong
russia
russia that is beaten back a russia that
is crippled is not good for india
and russia is most likely going to
achieve its objectives
in that case the chinese will also be
bolstered because they are essentially
using russia as a mercenary force right
now
so they are cooperating and coordinating
with russia
and they want to essentially create a
separate a parallel global system
a global system that is going to create
a bipolar world one will be the
us-dominated western world and the other
will be the eastern bloc russia and
china and whoever else comes with that
comes into that that orbit
so if russia is stronger if russia
succeeds it may actually be good for
india
it may give india
leverage in negotiations for the u.s
also
if russia loses then all the leverage is
gone so it's a complicated situation
but essentially a russian victory in the
long run
on the geopolitical chess board may
actually be favorable for india
if russia loses india loses a lot of its
leverage
and then india will have to go
completely into the u.s orbit
and it may
the u.s may
impose lots of conditions on india
okay this is an interesting question
lingua x dio says didn't change khan
have a rules based system
are there exceptions
you said that he invaded countries only
when his own country was wronged
did do you know what this is called it's
called having principles yes i said that
however you are correct that most
countries do act in the manner that you
described in the video so it's like this
when chingas khan ruled
over half the world he was the
superpower the mongol empire was the
superpower
and while he was alive
he ruled in a certain manner
he had like you say a rules-based system
he had principles and he acted according
to those principles so he invaded
countries only in retaliation only when
his own country was wronged and that's
the reason why he refused to invade
india even when he was in the doorstep
of india
even though india was
the wealthiest country in the world at
the time
so he had a rule-based system very
clearly he acted according to those
principles today those principles have
been dispensed with
mongolia is no longer a superpower it's
no longer even a small power
it's essentially insignificant today
half of mongolia is currently occupied
by china
today
the so-called rules based system is
based on the rules that the americans
set
and as we know they keep on changing the
rules as per their convenience
so
that's just how it goes the most
powerful country the the biggest power
is going to set the rules when it is
somebody who has actual principles the
rules are going to be
principled
and there will be
applied uniformly when
it is a power that is not that
principled you will have a system like
the way like the one that you have today
when they do it it's fine when somebody
else does it they need to be sanctioned
so that's just how it goes and that's
what we are witnessing but it's a very
interesting question you asked i had not
i had not thought of it in that way that
ching is khan had a rules-based system
but that's exactly what it is so you
it's a very interesting observation that
you have made
agusta said i've heard you say in tweet
that power is worth more than money when
it comes to geopolitics
why is it so and could you explain it in
to us in layman's terms yes i have said
this multiple times including in the
chungiskan video that power always
trumps wealth
power always trumps money
if you have money
then your money can always be taken away
by somebody who is powerful
but if you are powerful
then nobody can take your money away
from you and if you're powerful then you
can use money to buy more power
but if you are just wealthy but not
powerful you cannot use that money to
buy power so that's how it works so how
do i explain this in layman terms
so in 1994 i believe there was the
so-called uh
buddha pest
protocol budapest agreement
in so what happened in
during the breakup of the ussr was that
ukraine
had approximately
3 000
ussr nuclear warheads
on its territory
on ukrainian soil so ukraine became a
separate country
the ussr was too power to too weak to
prevent the breakup
of its uh of the country so ukraine
became a separate country an independent
country an independent republic it had 3
000 soviet nuclear weapons on its soil
and it gave away those nuclear weapons 3
000 nuclear weapons to russia
in exchange
for a guarantee
that the russians would
ensure that
the uss that ukraine would remain
peaceful
so in exchange for a guarantee of
protection and peace the ukrainians gave
away
nuclear all their nuclear weapons
and this was guaranteed by the the by
the russians by the americans and by
nato
so there were three guarantors
of
ukraine's
security in exchange for giving away
nuclear weapons now do you know what
nuclear weapons represent
they represent the ultimate power in the
world
if you have one nuke
one nuclear warhead you are powerful
the ukrainians had three 000 nuclear
warheads there is an immense amount of
power which they had in their hands
and they gave it away
to the russians
imagine if they had
even 30 nuclear warheads today
would mr putin have dared to invade
ukraine
that's what it is
that is this that is why power power is
more important than money
the ukrainians are wealthy
they are a resource rich country they
are a reasonably wealthy country but
that money is not going to save them
from the invasion
right
but if they if they had the power which
they gave up then the invasion would
never have happened
so you may be the wealthiest country in
the world like india was throughout its
history
india accounted for over a third of the
entire world's gdp
and when india had these powerful
empires nobody dared to invade but in
the past 1000 years because of political
fragmentation
india was invaded successfully slowly
over time and all the wealth was stolen
out stolen out of india
so your wealth is of no use unless you
are powerful if you unless you have you
have the power and you know how to use
it
excuse me so that illustrates the
difference between power and wealth and
it shows you why power is always more
important than wealth
okay rahul says what do you think of
vladimir putin's leadership he's made up
to be the villain among the westerners
but he's looking at his after his
national interests excuse me are they
justified to compare him with hitler who
was a monster
how would you compare putin's leadership
qualities with zelenski's
see mr zelinski
is by profession an entertainer an actor
and a comedian
you know the ancient romans said that
entertainers
should be kept far away from power
entertainers should be kept far away
from society they should live separately
right
so that was the rule that the romans had
and even vishnu gupta chanakya in the
arthashastra i think he mentions that
entertainer should be taxed highly and
kept separate from society
but today in today's world
our biggest role models in today's
society are entertainers actors and
actresses and all that
and that's why people like zelinski
because of their entertainment ability
and acting ability
become successful politicians even
though they may not have
the right kind of leadership ability
so putin is not an entertainer he's not
a funny guy i mean sometimes he may be
but that's not his primary
uh
call to fame
so putin is a genuine leader zelensky is
just a puppet he's a nato puppet he was
put in place because he was popular as a
as an entertainer
and that's how it went so there is no
comparison leadership and today the
media is trying to portray zelensky as a
very very uh
courageous figure wearing military
uniform and not giving up
and standing strong and giving wonderful
speeches even though the russians are
invading that is just media hype that is
not leadership
leadership is not quantified in the kind
of speeches you give like barack obama
leadership is all about actions
right
so what do i think about vladimir
putin's leadership well he's doing
whatever it takes to to safeguard
and promote
his national interest the interest of
his nation
and uh
the first principle of leadership
the non-negotiable quality a leader
needs to have
is that a leader should succeed
a leader has to succeed a leader must
succeed
a country that tolerates leaders who
fail
is doomed
that's what indians don't realize
because in the past 70 years we have
been tolerating leader after leader
after leader
who have failed
some of the most idolized so-called
leaders in india are failures
i think you can guess at some names
so the number one
rule of leadership number one rule of
leadership please remember this
a leader must succeed
so putin is succeeding and therefore
he's a good leader that's sim as simple
as that
priyanshu says everyone is talking about
what this country should do and what
that country should do but what about
the students and individuals who are all
studying in colleges and universities in
ukraine
all their years of effort and money are
in vain
because in the present world degree
matters in various fields like medicine
engineering etc they all have to start
from the beginning how can the
government help the students in terms of
education
yeah good question you are right all
those students
who have
who were in ukraine
i they will not be able to continue the
education there
and essentially
they have lost whatever whatever time
they spend in ukraine the thing is this
the government is not even duty bound
according to india's law and
constitution
to
organize an evacuation effort for indian
citizens but it still did that it
brought it is trying its best to bring
back all of them
the vast majority of them have already
been evacuated out of the country out of
ukraine and hopefully in the next 24 to
48 hours those who are left will be
taken out to safety
so that's the first thing the indian
government needs to focus on
in the long run
what can we do about those students who
lost everything we need to reform the
education system right now what we have
is most of the students i believe we're
studying
for a medical degree that's what i hear
and right now we have the scenario of
scarcity in the indian education system
we have so many students who want
medical degrees who need medical degrees
but we don't have enough seats for them
in our colleges in universities
so that is one of the problems i think
in the last five years
we have india has increased its capacity
in medical seats of by at least 70
percent in the next five years we may
double it from what it is today so if we
are able to do that then we will be able
to to absorb
the students
who are not able to get a seat in a
medical college or
or course in india and who are forced to
go abroad
so that's what we can do but as of now
what the indian government can do is to
ensure that everybody comes back safe
that's all we can do as of today
right and in the long run we need to
reform the education system
which is terrible
india's education system is terrible i
will get into get into that shortly
arjun singh rawat
uh says could you please shed some light
on chechnya
and the chechen separate special forces
who are believed to be one of the most
brutal and ruthless
soldiers in the world
it's a very interesting question
chechnya
so i could give you a three-hour account
of the history of chechnya which is very
interesting actually but
we don't have time for that so i'll make
it brief
chechny has an interesting history
as we know chechnya is an islamic muslim
republic in russia
let's see where it is
it's in the caucasus region
so
this here if you can see my mouse
pointer is the caspian sea
and this region here
is chechnya the capital city is grosney
all right
so it's in the caucasus region it is a
muslim republic in russia
now if you look at the history of
chechnya it it wasn't always muslim uh
the islamization of this region happened
in just in the last 200 or 300 years if
i'm not mistaken not it's not been a
long
it's not been a long time
so what is chechnya today
chechnya you could consider it to be
it's technically
a republic or or an administrative
division in russia
but the the more accurate way of looking
at chechnya today
is to consider it to be a
semi-autonomous kingdom
so chechnya is essentially a
within russia
the ruler or the king of chechnya
is uh
what's his name
was the father
what is his name i forget ramzan kadyrov
let me uh
let me share my screen
so the ruler or the or the king the de
facto king of chechnya
is
this gentleman here
so he is absolutely loyal to vladimir
putin
as you can see he's facing mr putin here
and in exchange for his absolute loyalty
he is he has been made the de facto king
of chechnya
and he has his own military his own
militia
so chechnya so if you look at russia
today
the overall uh growth of the population
is actually negative in russia so it is
below the replacement rate the total
fertility rate in russia is below the
replacement rate but in chechnya the
population is actually
rising
so the the the rate of births in
chechnya is greater than the rate of
deaths so chechnya is a great place from
where you can get soldiers for the
russian army and all of these soldiers
are
part of this private army of mr ramzan
kadyrov who is the son of ahmad khadirov
who was a former
rebel in chechnya so chechnya chechnya
tried to break free of russia became
become independent there were two
chechen wars one in the 1990s
under boris yelts
yeltsin yeah and the russians lost that
war
and then a second chechen war happened
under mr putin and the russians won
and
so some of the rebels became pro-putin
and ahmad khadirov's son is mr ramzan
kadyrov who is now the de facto king you
could say he is completely loyal to mr
putin he has his own army and his army
is
loyal to russia and whenever it is
needed
they will go and serve in the russian
army and take part in military
operations and that's what we are seeing
right now so i believe the chechens have
been sent into ukraine
and they will be deployed and sent into
battle into into a military operation if
they are needed and they have a
reputation of being very brutal
so
that's what i can explain in very brief
very interesting
part of the world
okay saurabh says what is the role of
japan in the whole geopolitical world
what are the choices of interest
for japan
the role of japan is not much
unfortunately today and let me explain
why
we have to go back to the map
so japan
is essentially a satellite state a
client state of the united states
i do not regard japan unfortunately
as a sovereign country
and let me tell you why
let me tell you why i do not regard
japan as a sovereign independent nation
see when you
when you have
a permanent military presence
of another country on your soil
you cannot be considered to be a
sovereign independent nation
let's go to okinawa shall we
so this is the island of okinawa in
japan
let's let's uh look at so as you can see
there are a couple of
couple of airports here
let's look at this one
it's called
now it's called the marine
corps air station futenma
so this is an american permanent
military base it's a permanent military
base american base the american marine
corps is stationed here
and their weapons and
aircraft and all that will be found here
so these are american
aircraft
these are
these are helicopters and and so on
so this is an american base in japan
permanent permanent base
this is another one
this is the kadena air base
a united states armed force base again
and if you look
at the kind of aircraft they've deployed
here
these are american fighter planes and so
on
right and i can show you lots of other
american military bases that have a
permanent deployment in japan
us
military
bases
japan let's see
so you will have more you will have many
more in the mainland also in the main
part of japan
us uh
let's search for that again
as you can see
throughout japan
so japan essentially
can be considered rightfully to be under
american occupation
so what is the role of japan to do
whatever the americans tell them
that is the role of japan japan has been
under american occupation since 1945
since the end of the second world war
the japanese constitution was written
drafted
under american supervision it has not
been changed
as far as i know since the americans
drafted it
we had leaders like mr abe mr shinzo abe
who were in favor of changing the
constitution allowing the japanese armed
forces to have a more
proactive and
significant role
but for some reason mr abe had to step
down from the prime ministership
apparently because of health reasons
and now he's no longer in power now we
have a bunch of anonymous
prime ministers one after the other will
come and go come and go come and go
so japan doesn't have much of a role in
geopolitics it is a powerful country
it has excellent submarines
uh the chinese the chinese are scared of
the japanese submarines it has an ex
excellent
military
sorry industrial base
it is the most technologically advanced
nation in the world
right
you could consider japan to be a shadow
nuclear power
if they want
they can have nuclear weapons next week
that's how advanced their technology is
and that's how advanced their
technological capabilities are they also
have a very advanced space program very
good rockets and all that so they could
have
nukes next week they could have delivery
systems for the new for the nukes next
week
but
they are under u.s occupation
the americans will not allow them to do
it unless the americans deem it to be
useful for america for the american
national interest so that is the role
right now of japan in geopolitics not
very significant japan is not
really a sovereign nation unfortunately
sorry hersh over he says whose strategy
is working effectively nato with its
economic sanctions and freezing of
russian assets or russia with its
offensive and gas oil related prior
price pay
what's going to happen who will pin out
first according to this it is still to
be seen it's too early to say who's
going to win
uh the russians
have opted for a military strategy for a
military
uh incursion
intervention in ukraine and thus far
it's working fine
most likely in the next 10 days they
will achieve their objectives
so from that perspective they're doing
well their strategy is working
nato has dumped
the mother of all sanctions
on
russia the americans have dumped the
entire kitchen sink at russia
all the sanctions you can imagine
they've thrown at them
so essentially it gives russia nothing
more to lose
so what the americans have done
believe it or not
is they have pushed russia
into the chinese arms
the russia the americans by doing all
this have precipitated
the bipolarization of the world the
chinese and the russians will
now go ahead and try to create
a separate international system
right
and they may even want who knows india
to be part of the system
so if the russians succeed in what they
are doing
then
it may give more leverage to india
in negotiating with the us
if it has an offer
of joining this parallel system
but india obviously needs to be very
careful because china is always a threat
so that's where we are right now so the
americans what they have done it looks
like it's been very counterproductive
it's going to precipitate the
bipolarization of the world
it's going to show the world that
american hegemony no longer
works all the time they were not able to
prevent the russians from taking over
ukraine
ukraine was supposed to be in the
american orbit the next nato member
state and see what happened they could
not save ukraine
what about you next can they save you so
that's what we are seeing so we are
witnessing the slow
decline
of
american power
so i would say that in the long run it
looks like the american empire is now in
decline
and an eastern front may be in the
ascendancy but we it still remains to be
seen
see no power will
decline without a fight
especially when you are becoming weaker
you will lash out more aggressively
so that's why the next decade is going
to be a decade possibly of great chaos
the russians may now try to bring
iran
into their fold the iranians have been
crippled by american sanctions for the
past god knows how many years
right
they the americans walked back from the
iran nuclear deal
unilaterally after signing the agreement
in an international agreement they
backstabbed iran so the iranians are
will be very happy to go into the
eastern bloc with the russians and the
chinese
the pakistanis are already under the
chinese umbrella
so you could see a very rapid
bipolarization of the world and then it
will be up to india to decide what it
wants to do what is best for india's
national interest in the long run
so that's what we are witnessing right
now the world is in flux
uh nepal oh
hello
okay let me read this out then i will
remove this
so uh the first question is
yes abhijit this is the best way to
repay all the gurkha soldiers who have
sacrificed their lives for india
they have fought two wars before
retirement and you thank them for the
service by invading their homeland
and swadesh kharki says i am from nepal
currently in the u.s
it's a long
long
couple of paragraphs what he's saying is
that in nepal there are very limited
people who understand all this and their
minds have been completely brainwashed
and so on yes okay
so i had said in one of the last in one
of last week's
live streams
that in case china invades taiwan
india needs to secure
nepal and sri lanka that's what i had
said
and
it looks like many people have
interpreted this as
me trying to say that india needs to
invade and occupy nepal
see
let's understand the india-nepal
relationship
this gentleman
mentioned the gurkha soldiers
let's understand the india-nepal
relationship it is a privileged
relationship
india and nepal have an open border
indians don't need a visa to go to nepal
nepalese people don't need a visa to
come to india the border is open you can
just walk in and walk out
the citizens of nepal
have the right
to come to india
work in india
and live in india as long as they want
their whole life if they want they have
the right to do this they have the
privilege of doing this
and the citizens of the citizens of
nepal
have the privilege have the right
to serve in the indian armed forces
in the indian army in the defense of
india
that is a privilege that only the
citizens of nepal have
citizens of any other country don't have
any of these privileges
we don't have an open border with
pakistan afghanistan
after the question temporarily we don't
have an open border with pakistan with
bangladesh bangladesh
burma sri lanka anything only the
nepalese citizens have these rights and
privileges and vice versa it works both
ways
so it's a privileged relationship we
have an open border
right
and
so i will be perfectly happy
if nepal remains an independent country
in this manner
for the rest of eternity
i said india needs to secure nepal's
territorial integrity because we know
what the chinese have been doing
they have taken over the whole of tibet
they are biting at our natural they are
they are taking bites out of bhutan
they are taking bites off of all of
their neighbors
they will in the case of a conflict with
india try to use nepalese territory to
to make incursions into india
they will not respect nepal's
territorial integrity or sovereignty
and like the other gentleman said
nepalese have been brainwashed today
right and the roots of that lie in the
regime change that was done in the 1990s
when the maoists came to power and the
nepalese monarchy was destroyed
right and after the mouse came to power
the entire brainwashing of of youngsters
started and today it looks like lots of
nepalese have a very strong anti-india
sentiment let me tell something to tell
you guys something my nepalese friends
in case you're watching
we are the same people
the nepalese
are the descendants of lord rahm lord
krishna
right
and so are the indians
i mean i i believe that one of the
previous nepalese prime ministers even
tried to claim that lord rama was born
in nepal and so on
so we are the same people
indians are the descendants of the
mauryans so are the nepalese we're the
same people
we have an open border let it remain the
way it is india doesn't have any
uh ambitions to take away nepal
sovereignty i think nepal has done very
well it has in some ways been able to
preserve its culture better than india i
think it would be best if india doesn't
dump socialism and secularism on nepal
right
so
india needs to secure nepal's
territorial integrity and sovereignty in
case of any chinese misadventure that's
all all i was saying and the same goes
for sri lanka
indians like to talk about these days
about akanda bharat akanda bharat
doesn't need to be a single monolithic
empire it can be a confederation
of allied states who all share the same
culture and civilization it doesn't mean
that they have to be under one single
political dispensation
right
so we can have
a united states of akanda bharat with a
number of independent sovereign states
within them but who all share the same
culture
and civilization in the long run not
today tomorrow next week
so
please understand that i do not have
any i am not recommending that india
should invade nepal
and take away nepal sovereignty nepal is
doing very well on its own
and we have an excellent
open privileged relationship with nepal
why can't it continue the same way if
tibet had been independent we would have
had most likely
a similar kind of relationship with
tibet as well with open borders and so
on so forth maybe
when the world is a better place we can
have that too but please understand my
nepalese friends we have no
ambitions of taking over nepal
we just want nepal to stay secure and
sovereign and independent
and please understand this china is not
your friend
china is not the friend of the nepalese
people or the nepalese nation it's not
okay let's take one more question
education
clear warning very demonic our education
system is garbage mind your language
brother
and the other person is saying we our
country has the most intellectuals in
the world
and uh
and we have
we are building uae we have sewage
workers
and i.t field and all that so never
bring down your motherland in your heart
even on especially on an open platform
do correct your viewpoint
and there's more indian education system
is not garbage don't speak irresponsibly
please don't say it is garbage our
education system is on par with the
global system
and janavi says please don't comment on
anything you're not sure of please get
you get your facts right
your comments are not ridiculing the
education system is not in good taste
and so on and so forth so that's what
many people are saying because last week
i had said
that india's education system is garbage
maybe i used a very strong term
but
i stand by what i said
india's education system is one of the
worst in the world
you all
my dear friends i don't blame you for
feeling this way
but
please realize
that the education system is not serving
unity let me show you okay so let me
tell you what is wrong with the
education system there is extremely poor
quality of faculty and teachers do you
realize that there is a lot of politics
in the education system you have
reservations you have incompetence in
this in the staff in the teachers the
education system prioritizes the staff
over the students there is a
commercialization of the education
system degrees are a commodity to be
sold these days you are forced to
memorize things not to understand
anything you don't know what is right or
wrong what is good or bad you're not
taught these things you are not allowed
to question the teacher you are forced
to be in under a state of absolute
obedience
the education system tells you what to
think not how to think
it educates you just enough to believe
what they teach you but not enough for
you to question what they teach you do
you know that the basic qualification
required for a clerk
is the same as the basic education
required for an is officer graduation
the degrees are worthless the education
is in a foreign language it's creating
cyber coolies you have this artificial
scarcity
more students less seats
india is spending billions of dollars in
foreign exchange to stay to send
students to other countries to educate
them and you know what's the funny thing
when indian students go to foreign
countries to get an education they
mostly study under indian professors who
are working there do you understand how
terribly broken the education system is
so india's education system is terrible
whether you realize it or not please
don't react emotionally when you come
across information that you don't expect
or you don't agree with try and
understand what the person is trying to
say and if you are truly
if you are truly interested in
understanding what is wrong with the
education system then i can i can
give you
a pointer
i will give you a recommendation
uh just one thing let me let me share my
screen
so if you are truly interested in
knowing what is wrong with the education
system watch episode
30. ask abhijit episode 30 on this
channel it is available on this channel
please what watch this episode if you
are truly interested in understanding
what is what are the problems and what
is what are the solutions that we need
to implement in the indian education
system
so that is what i will leave you with we
have crossed the two hour mark so let us
end
this session for today
so thank you everybody for watching and
once again let me before i end
uh remind you that i have created a
separate new channel short clips channel
the link is in the description
uh go to the description and the link is
also here it is youtube.com
in case you want to watch short clips of
each individual answer instead of
watching a two hour long session which i
would be which i would perfectly
understand why then please subscribe to
this channel
all right everybody thank you very much
for very interesting questions tomorrow
i will take more questions tomorrow i
will do i will take some questions from
video chat as well
so
i look forward to seeing you tomorrow
until then take care thank you very much
bye